hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream 71.1 on February
22nd 2024
222222 and we're here with Ryan Smith
Rowan Hodson and Mishka meta there will
be a quick overview and then discussion
on their recent work the empirical
status of predictive coding and active
confence so thank you all
and let's hear about
it um okay so you just want me to jump
in and go
yeah okay cool well thanks a ton Daniel
for um you know inviting us on um you
know fun to get to uh present some of
this stuff and you know hopefully get it
out to the the broader Community a
little bit um so just I'm gonna quickly
just kind of walk through sections of
the paper to orient people to generally
what the point is and what we're trying
to do and then um at that point I think
the goal is just to kind of launch it a
discussion and um see if we can kind of
extract out some of the more the more
interesting points that might be most um
you know relevant or interesting to the
active Insurance Community um so just to
um to start out with here so the paper
as Daniel said is called the empirical
status of predictive coding and active
inference um the main point of this is
just that you know as a lot of people in
this community know um it's you know at
its kind of beginning and for a long
time time um you know like the active
inferences primarily so the literature
you'll see has been um very focused on
theoretical um sort of conceptual work
and um and simulation based work right
so you'll see a lot of things out there
that's kind of you know an active
inference model of X um where X is just
some interesting psychological um
phenomena or condition um and usually
that involves showing some you know fun
interesting simulations um that are kind
of potential computational explanations
for you know whatever the you know
specific phenomenon of interest is um
and that work is great and I think
there's been a lot of developments there
but um you know at a certain point um
you know we can come up with as many
theories as we want um but without
actually being able to test them
scientifically um it's really hard to be
able to say with any confidence that
these are kind of accurate stories of
what the brain's doing and what are the
kind of yeah again like empirically
supported um um Theory you know what
which of all these sort of models than
simulations people are proposing sort of
actually correspond to what the brain's
doing and whether they can actually
explain uh human
behavior um so what we were interested
in doing is actually kind of taking a
step back and um looking at what the
what the empirical studies that have um
been done using um these sorts of
modeling approaches um what they
actually say um and how supportive the
the evidence actually is for um you know
the hypothesis that the brain is doing
things like predictive coding and active
inference so that's why it's called the
empirical status right as we're trying
to say okay what is the current evidence
um and where is evidence missing right
so what should future work um and future
studies focus on to um to try to
actually you know like like fill in and
answer questions and provide additional
support or not um for you know for um
for these theories as hypotheses for
what um for what the brain is doing um
so to kind of walk through sections here
so we focused you know so people use
this umbrella term of like predictive
processing but that's really a fairly
vague overarching kind of umbrella term
um and so we picked kind of the primary
you know actually sort of like
well-defined algorithms you know in um
that are most prominent within the kind
of under the predictive processing
umbrella which is predictive coding and
active inference these are kind of well-
defined mathematical algorithms um that
can be sufficiently precise to to test
empirically um so the first section is
more or less just kind of an
introduction that says more or less the
sort of thing I just said about um
predictive coding and active inference
being the kind of most prominent um
precisely formulated algorithms um that
the brain might be doing and the
importance of testing these things
empirically etc etc um and so um I
should say that you know most of the
credit for this paper should really go
to the first author which is Rowan
Hudson here who I'm hoping will um
certainly say much more after I give
this kind of brief overview um but you
know so what Rowan did is he started out
um in each of these sections by defining
the algorithm and laying out the the the
the associated mathematics um in a way
that was uh really very clear I thought
um of course I'm bragging a little bit
about a paper that I'm on so take that
with a grain of salt but um but I
thought he did a very good job of laying
it out you know being explicit showing
the mathematics but describing it in a
way that was um um what I think should
be very accessible to people that don't
have a ton of mathematical background um
and the idea was that we would just you
know introduce this so that what we were
talking about was clear um but the focus
really isn't on you know just the
mathematics we're just in introducing a
mathematics so it can be kind of more
understandable what um you know what the
studies that we review are actually
testing um and so so we just kind of
walk through a lot of the and I'll come
back to this figure in a second but you
know the the underlying mathematics of
for instance you know here is a
definition of the negative free energy
um when when applied within predictive
coding um and just kind of how you get
to some of the predictions and
prediction errors and things like that
that we actually use um and uh this this
figure is a figure that took a long time
to make and to try to be clear on but
you know we thought it ended up um being
pretty uh you know colorful and and uh
engaging and and it looks complicated
but um we tried pretty hard to kind of
walk people through step by step what
this is what this is hypothesizing but
this is just a representation of one way
that um cortical columns in the brain
might Implement hierarchical predictive
coding and this is a particular form of
a particular predictive coding algorithm
that um allows for a certain type of
temporal depth to it
um where where you have um essentially a
higher level hidden cause that's being
represented that actually predicts
Dynamics in the representations at the
level below as opposed to just
predicting and trying to minimize
prediction eror with respect to some
sort of static um equivalent temporal
scale representation at the level below
um so we try to kind of lay that out um
so that people have an understanding of
what again what the kind of General
basis and what the hypothesis is um it's
kind of important here because
predictive coding at an algorithmic
level is a different thing to test than
than trying to test a theory about the
the specific neural mechanisms that
Implement predictive coding right so so
it's I think it's a really important
point is is that you can test a theory
empirically by looking at the brain to
try to like test a hypothesis about a
specific way the brain could be set up
to do predictive coding but the brain
could be the brain could be set up in
more than one way that would Implement
predictive coding so to be specific
about testing something about the brain
process you need to specify what
algorithm you want to see whether
there's evidence that the brain is doing
that um more generally though you could
also just test for evidence of
predictive coding at the algorithmic
level and you could do that behaviorally
just by looking at whether you know
people's people's what people detect
perceptually and how that evolves over
time um whether that is just consistent
with the with with the predictive coding
algorithm so just just the mathematics
not some more specific hypothesis about
the way the brain is doing it um through
different patterns of
connectivity um so then as I mentioned
we kind of go through um now just uh we
lay out what the proposed neural
implementation is or as I said one
commonly proposed implementation there's
actually a couple that we talk about um
and then here in this section we have
the empirical studies of predictive
coding and we review more or less what
the evidence is um for these different
uh for for um different kind of aspects
or um testing different predictions um
that predictive coding might make about
what you would see um either
behaviorally or or in the brain um and I
won't kind of go into it in detail here
we can obviously talk about it when we
get more into the discussion but um you
know take-home is is really there is a
lot of indirect evidence um but um more
there's a lot of studies that still kind
of remain to be done to test more
specific hypotheses about the neural
implementation um you know whether or
not for example there actually are
separate neurons in the brain that are
responding just to prediction erors and
other ones that are representing just
predictions and and things like that um
there really is more kind of explicit
model fitting that needs to be done to
test out this you know predictions
associated with really with quantitative
simulations um and what those predict um
based on the predictive coding algorithm
um one place where probably the most
kind of related evidence is is um not
with predictive coding proper but with
hierarchical gaussian Filter um which is
a a different model than predictive
coding but it um it has related it has
it predicts dynamics that are related to
predictive coding um so for instance it
does have prediction errors in it and it
does have a Precision waiting on those
predictions um and it can be the up
updates can be modeled in relation to
prediction errors and um one one
difference though is um instead of being
hierarchical in the sense of each level
in a hierarchy representing different
causes um in the hierarch Gan filter
higher levels represent predictions
about the the stability of the
contingencies at the level below so so
basically the highest level is
representing something like how quickly
it expects the um predictive
relationship between hidden States and
outcomes how how quickly it expects
those will change over time um and so it
can do this kind of like Dynamic
Precision um waiting depending on
essentially how much you should trust
the predictions you have in a given
moment based on how you think those
predictive relationships will change
over time so it's not the same thing as
predictive coding but it's related and
people have done neuroimaging studies um
for example um and looked at the
explicit relationship between the
prediction ER dynamics that this model
um the predictions it makes about those
prediction and prediction ER Dynamics
and whether or not you can find uh
neural responses that look like they
match um those predicted simulated time
courses um and there have't been a few
studies that do support um the specific
brain regions are encoding prediction
errors and predictions and things like
that um um and different uh precisions
um so it's not the same thing as testing
for decoding directly but it is testing
um and finding evidence for a neural
basis of um of encoding of precision
weighted prediction erors which again
overlaps in interesting ways um as kind
of again indirect but but important
evidence um so then um after we go
through that then we switch to talking
about active inference um and again kind
of similar structure um first uh Rowan
introduced the mathematics um associated
with the active inference framework um
and you know for people that are
watching uh this you know this um U you
know the active inference Institute um
program um regularly um should be aware
that active inference you know nowadays
has evolved into um kind of also being a
broader umbrella term for multiple
different um specific mathematical
formalisms um and uh so to be clear this
this one that we go through here is is
just the kind of standard initial
partially observable Markov decision
process framework um so this is a
specific model of decision making um
based on a particular explore exploit
trade-off in a model based way um where
instead of just using reward um as a
cost function um or an objective
function um it's based on the expected
free energy which is just this
combination of expected reward and
expected Information Gain um so it's a
it's a talking about a specific
algorithm and kind of the original
algorithm under under active inference
but now there's there's lots of
different kind of variants of it um so
we're just going through the basic one
um so again you know we talk about how
it's related to predictive coding um and
what's different about it from
predictive coding and then um in this
case uh what we do is there there is
actually um quite a bit more um in
active inference at least this version
of it um there are a number of empirical
studies that have directly um fit active
inference models to decisionmaking
behavior um you know several of these
come out of um our lab actually um but
there are some other ones that haven't
and um so we we reviewed um each of
these in in detail kind of laid out how
the model um how the models were set up
um to model specific decisionmaking or
um or perceptual decision- making TX
tasks um you know so for instance here
we kind of introduced a the model for a
specific task but used to model
interception so cardiac
interception um and then yeah here you
can just see this is just kind of a
standard you know version of a depiction
of the active inference um
model um and then let's see you know
again these are sort of standard things
you see in lots of active inference
papers right so just describing and
laying out the mathematics of the of the
general update equations and the the
overall algorithm and then um a very
kind of coar grain generic sort of
representation of one way that the brain
might Implement those those algorithms
kind of inspired by cortical column
structure um but so anyway you can see
this is a model that we used to an
active inference model we set up to
model a three Arm Bandit task um that we
used in um in substance use disorders to
show that um and in this one you know
what we were able to show for example
was that um substance users showed
slower learning rates from negative
outcomes than healthy individuals so you
can see it's much more based on trying
to answer psychiatric questions about
clinical groups because our our lab is
focused on computational Psychiatry um
in
particular um so we walk through that we
walked through a task that we modeled
using an approach avoidance conflict um
Paradigm and that model also was able to
show differences in decision uncertainty
and um what we call emotion conflict
it's a type of preference Precision
effectively um that um also differed in
affec of disorders and substance use
disorders from healthy controls in an
interesting way um there was also a
couple others one really cool study that
was um not by us but got by um gson was
the first author um and they took they
took for example a set of publicly
available data sets for uh what's called
a two-step task which is just a common
task used in reinforcement learning
models and um in that task uh there's a
standard reinforcement learning model
that's used that's a essentially kind of
a mixture-based model of of what a model
free reinforcement learning model versus
a modelbased reinforcement learning
model would predict um and the the what
that task was designed to do um
initially was to use this kind of
mixture reinforcement learning model to
test individual differences in how um
kind of modelbased versus model free
people are um if um we can talk about
that a little more if people you know
listening aren't totally familiar with
the model based versus model fre
distinction but um but what they did
which was really which was really cool
was they um took that data and fit an
active inference model to it and then
compared the ability of active inference
to explain um Behavior compared to the
standard reinforcement learning model I
just mentioned and um what they were
able to show is that the active
inference model um in two of the four
data sets um was actually a little bit
better um at explaining the behavioral
patterns than the um than the
reinforcement learning model was in the
other two data sets the models were
about equivalent um so so that was
probably the most direct evidence um
that um that has been shown and this was
a one of the major points I think that
that we wanted to make is that even
though it's the case that you know us
and other people have started to do
actual empirical studies trying to fit
active inference models to data um the
main purpose so far and what people have
done really hasn't been to provide
unique evidence for active inference
it's just been using active inference um
as a way to try to identify individual
differences or group differences in in a
um psychiatric research context um so so
one thing that is still really needed um
aside from this one gchen study I
mentioned um is more studies where
people will actually take um you know
behavioral data or collect behavioral
data um on decision-making tasks and fit
a bunch of fit different active
inference models to it and also fit a
bunch of sort of competing models like
reinforcement learning models to it um
to really show that the active inference
the the behavioral patterns that active
inference predicts are um that that
active inference can can do a better job
of predicting that behavior than
competing models um can
because that's really the only way it's
not enough basically to show that active
inference models fit well you need to
show that active inference models fit
better than um competing models because
that's how you'd really show that um
that active inference is more likely
what the brain is doing when people are
making decisions um and so you know the
the overarching conclusion is that um
you know the the evidence is is
promising right I mean there's nothing
that suggests that the brain isn't doing
active inference um and and certainly
it's consistent with people doing active
people using active inference but um a
lot more still needs to be done to show
that active inference is a is a better
explanation for what people do than
simpler competing models um so that's
you know just as a a kind of broad brief
overview of the the general structure of
the paper and the message we were trying
to get across um so you know we can we
can certainly talk about it more um just
kind of interactively now um lots that I
didn't talk about um but hopefully that
starts as just kind of an initial
launching point for for a discussion so
um I guess I'll just stop
there thank you awesome perhaps the
other authors could give the first takes
introduce
thems sure I'll start um yeah I'm I'm
Rowan um I'm a PhD student uh Ryan's my
supervisor I'm at Institute for brain
research um I did my masters at the
University of Cape Town under Jonathan
shock Mark SS and Ryan as well um I
think yeah just to talk a bit more
generally about this paper this this
paper started off as um a book chapter
actually which was only going to be
focused on Act of inference and sort of
especially uh particularly empirical
states of act difference and in the
process of writing this um I filed
myself uh what needing almost to write
about predictive coding um it's it's I
think whenever we can we should take the
opportunity to
really um present this in a in a very
methodical and complete way and I think
sometimes I remember when I was first
learning about active reference it's
very hard to dive in in the into the
middle and I think that's how it sort of
became it morphed from just being
focused on active inference to being
focused on active inference and
predictive coding where you Prive coding
acts as a sort of foundation um for a
large aspect of active
inflence um and I think that's how that
sort of happened and then of course it
morphed a little bit from just uh just
talking about predictive studies to also
talking about the sort of the the
background mathematics and the
theoretical foundations and so I I think
this is the sort of field where um it's
a noble cause to try whenever we can get
the opportunity to try present a a quite
a thorough review of all aspects of this
because um it's a difficult field to
learn uh it can be very confusing so
yeah I really hope that this review on
top of presenting the empirical side of
things also acts as uh a reasonbly
intuitive way to look at the
foundational theory of PR coding
acence yeah and one thing one thing I
will say just to kind of add to that is
is that um you know for for people that
you know have more of a kind of broad
conception or philosophical interest in
um inactive inference as opposed to you
know more the kind of like detailed
mathematical modeling sort of
understanding um often what I've seen in
the past is is that um predictive coding
and active inference get a little bit
kind of conflated right so you know
people think that active inference is
somehow just predictive coding plus
motor control or plus decision- making
or something and so making it clear
that's actually really not the case I
think is important right that predictive
coding is actually an entirely different
algorithm it has a different generative
model associated with it um you know it
uses continuous date spaces whereas
active inference uses discret State
spaces and discreet time like to really
lay out like I think Rowan did very well
um you know with mishka's help also um
was um you know to kind of state clearly
what the connection is between
predictive coding and active inference
but but that they are not the same thing
and they're not even directly connected
to each other so to make that to make
that a little bit more more clear and
more intuitive maybe so that was just
another thing I wanted to say that I
thought I thought that they um that they
did pretty well and there another kind
of maybe useful take home point from the
paper hi I'm arishka um so I'm also like
Rowan a second year PhD student at The
laurate Institute and Ryan is my
supervisor my background is more um
neuroscience and psychology so this
paper was like a really cool and
challenging first step in my PhD where I
come from a more empirical background so
kind of working on this paper was uh
kind of going not taking baby step but
deep dive into the active inference and
the predictive coding
literature and again um I'm the people
that Ryan was talking about who had more
interest on the empirical side and kind
of going through this journey like
really helped me like walk step by step
into like different aspects of the just
like pred cing or active um inference
literature that you should take into
consideration and think about really
like the algorithmic side the neural
side of things and kind of like
connecting those three levels how we how
different people kind of just think
about from one perspective but what
really is needed is connecting all those
three things and I felt like I was
playing a supportive role in this paper
but this really was a great Learning
Journey for
me
okay why not to Mr empirical
Dean um so my interest in This was um
anytime I see a title where there's a
minimum of two uh ideas being brought
together as the unit unit of analysis
I'm I'm always curious is it okay if I
just because I have one question that's
sort of an unpacking question around
predictive coding and one question
related to active inference at the
conclusion would it be okay if I read a
little section of the
paper to
maybe pull it apart unpack
it s you just start just just start just
there's a little microphone thing could
you just repeat again okay so I'm I'm on
page eight of the paper and the section
I just like to get a little bit of
unpacking around is thus fitting
predictive coding models to responses on
perception tasks and testing with
quantitative predictions from
simulations remains an important
direction for work going forward this is
crucial because simulated Dynamics and
predictive coding models can make
predictions that are not always
straightforward a priori and that
depend like this depend on the specific
hypothesis built into a formal model
Ryan kind of touched on that in his
introduction for example the specific
mathematical form assumed by the mapping
between levels in a hierarchy the
direction in which neural activity is
assumed to represent a particular
posterior estimate often this is the
thing I was hoping somebody could unpack
for me often sequential
dependencies between task trials and
patterns and Dynamics can be missed in
summary statistics that average over
trials so models are necessary to
predict and test for the presence of
those precise D Dynamics I was hoping
maybe somebody could feel put some color
on that that process and what it
[Music]
means um sure I can take a stab at that
and um I mean you know Rowan or Mishka
can as well but I'll um I I'm pretty
sure that was something that I wrote so
maybe sense for for me to be the one to
at least take a start on it um so yeah I
mean that in in so in the field of
computational Psychiatry more broadly
right so not just active inference but
um you know the goal is really just
to take a take a set of task Behavior
right so we can ask people to do say
some kind of like sequential decision-
making task that involves um usually
like explore exploit dynamics of some
form right so so say like one common one
would be I give people like a three Arm
Bandit task right so I give people they
play some little game and there's three
different options and they don't know
what the reward probabilities are um so
and then they can just trial and error
in the beginning they can say choose
option three and they can see whether
they win or lose and if they win you
know let's say they probably stick with
option three again um but if they lose
maybe they try option two and then say
if they lose again they could try option
three again or they could try option one
um and so on and so forth right and so
predictive and active inference model in
this case I'm just using this as a kind
of a simpler starting example um an
active inference model um under
different parameter settings in that
model right under different learning
rates or under different um um directed
exploration drives or what however you
want to parameterize it um would make
different predictions about what that
sequence of choices would be um and
there's a sequential dependence because
the choices on each trial are not
independent right so what a person
chooses um on trial two depends very
much on the outcome they saw at trial
one um and what they see in option three
what they choose in option three will
depend on both what they saw Cho you
know after Choice One and choice two um
so if I do this standard right empirical
thing that you would like analytic thing
that you would do for a task like that
that's not model based is you might just
have some summary statistics right you
might do something like a common thing
to do would just be to count the number
of times they switched what option they
chose after they lost or how many times
they stuck with the same Choice after
they lost so we call those like win
stays or win switches um or same thing
like if you lose did you STI the stick
with the same one or did you switch so
this win stay win shift lose stay lose
shift you could just kind of count the
proportions of those right so you could
see something that you know maybe you
know how often people um lose switch for
example might might tell you something
kind of like their learning rate for
losses right like they they might learn
more quicker they might learn more
quickly right update their beliefs more
after a loss um if they if they're the
kind of person that switches away right
they'd be more quick to assume okay if
this option led to a loss this time um
that's probably not a good option
anymore so I'm going to switch to
something else right whereas if a person
has a slow learning rate for losses then
maybe they'll stick to the same one a
couple times before they decide okay
this is definitely a bad option they'
have to see like a few losses in a row
right so but the point is is that if all
you do is kind of average over trials
and get some kind of summary statistic
about how many times people you know win
shifted or lose State Etc um what you're
not going to get is anything about the
pattern in the Dynamics right so if they
like for instance if they like lose
shifted in the early first few choices
right like that tells you something
pretty different than if they lose stay
or lose shift on some of those later
choices um right the early choices might
be driven much more by like exploratory
drives right by information seeking
whereas on later trials that much might
be much better explained by differences
in learning rates um so so fitting
models to behavior which again just
means you have the actual behavior and
then you see what the model predicts
under a bunch of different different
parameter values right and you try to
find the parameter values for a person
that best reproduces their behavior
right so point is this is that we've
done that kind of thing several times
now for active inference right which you
can do with just by taking patterns of
decisions right that people make on
games um but you can do that same thing
for predictive coding right you can give
people perceptual decision-making tasks
right where people say okay this is what
I perceive this time okay this is what I
perceived this time Etc and those are
also going to have sequential
dependencies because people are going to
build up prior expectations about what
they're going to see next right um and
so predictive coding models again under
certain parameter values might say okay
well if they saw the same thing the last
five times they're GNA probably a lot
more biased right they're probably going
to have a much more precise prior that
they're going to see that again so the
probability they're going to say they
saw that again even if you showed
something different would be would be
higher right and so and so there are the
point is is that it's not always the
case that predictive a predictive coding
model is going to predict some
trajectory of choices that's going to be
really obvious without actually fitting
the model um you know if if for instance
the person like has no tendency
whatsoever to um be more likely to say
they saw one thing just because they saw
it a bunch more times in the past right
um that wouldn't really be very
consistent with the idea that people are
using predictive coding um um and um it
gets even a little trickier than that
because predictive coding is um based on
the continuous State space so it's not
really even something like a person
would be you know just like choosing I
saw this I saw that it'd be much more
something like them kind of continuously
turning a dial or something you know as
they see something get brighter or
dimmer or you know like Motion in a
Direction or another Direction and um
because the prediction error equations
are are set up in this kind of
continuous way they also have these kind
of like oscillatory Dynamics to them
right so it's like not like you get
error and then it drops as the thing
resolves but it kind of oscillates up
and down a little bit right and so that
would also predict pretty kind of
sometimes funny like not definitely not
something you could just predict a
priori like exactly how someone's gonna
like turn a dial um so that's that's the
kind of thing I mean okay uh
in my in very simple terms Daniel and I
have had some conversations around if
you're in a and if you're in a situation
where your focus or your concentration
is on the next move or if you can look
and see the entire space and take an all
moves perspective so my asking you the
question was to get out of the sort of
model piece of it and that so what what
do people actually do and I think your
the question around the oscill the
answer around the oscillation sort of
speaks to that it's it's difficult when
you're focusing on that next part of the
sequence to be able to take in the
entirety of the and vice versa if you're
focusing on the averages maybe you're
not able to pick up on the nuances of
The Next Step can I ask one more
question sure or would the other authors
like to continue to fill in on that
first answer um I think Ryan explained
that very well I think this is a general
um I'll talk about I know we that is
referring to predictive coding but in
something like something I'm very
interested in active inference is along
the lines of differentiating for example
between um a model that uses
reinforcement learning and a model that
uses active inference and um yeah using
summary statistics sometimes it can be
hard to actually see differential
Behavior right this is what we care
about when we are looking at comparing
different models what do they actually
predict differential behavior and that
differential Behavior can be difficult
to capture in summary statistics
sometimes um so in general I think in
the world of sort of um yeah model
fitting this is just a common common
theme and as Ryan said while we're doing
the stive reference they are limited
limited applications of that methodology
inli coding
so okay Mish is so I'll ask this the
other thing this was in in the
conclusion of the paper um again I'll
just read it in contrast to predictive
coding research in contrast predictive
coding research can be traced back
nearly four decades and make specific
predictions that can be investigated
across a variety of fields so there's a
deeper well of priors there I assume
that's what that means um it will be an
important direction for future research
to further develop the neural process
Theory underlying Act of inference and
allow for precise implementation level
as opposed to Simply algorithmic level
predictions about brain and behavior I
completely agree until that time
confidence and active inference as a
neural model of decision- making should
remain tentative but this is the part
that I thought was really interesting he
wrote another important limitation
associated with the current active
inference scheme is that of
scalability which constrains the
phenomena that can be examined in
empirical studies that is while these
models work well in the context of
simple tasks become less tractable if
applied to many real world problems with
high dimensional sets of States
observations and policies my question
was um is the idea of strategy because
it's active inference is known kind of
as a basis for strategizing behavior is
the is the question around scalability
one that ties into the idea that even
when humans are are trying to
strategize
um how far out they can generalize their
strategy is a
difficult measure to get
precise given that most context are
Dynamic and
changing so there's there's several kind
of related things here um so so the the
tractability issue kind of comes in two
different flavors so one flavor is
tractability with respect to like our
that our ability to like use these
models to even simulate behavior um in
in in contexts where the the kind of
space of options and how far in the
future people are planning right when
that gets big right the other the other
question is more about psychological
plausibility which is that um even if I
can get you know an active inference
model to simulate kind of like St 10
steps ahead and you know where there's
like ends up being like 30 or 40
different combinations of like 10 moves
or something like that right um it's not
really very plausible that humans are
really doing that right that the brain
is really doing that and you know
standard computer it's G to take like I
don't know like Rowan you know Rowan has
these fun planning models that he has
this paper that um you know we uh I
think are pretty close to submitting
there's a preprint of an earlier version
that's out um where you know the thing
does like plan right a bunch of
different possible paths that it can
take to you know find you know different
sorts of rewards um and uh you know it
takes like hours right to run like
simulations on a computer to do
something that however humans are doing
it they can do it just like you know in
a minute or something right right so so
um you know I don't so it's just not
very plausible that the way that active
inference is solving problems like that
um is in any kind of exact form the same
way the humans are doing it um so
there's kind of scalability with respect
to what humans can do because humans
can't do this explicitly in a fully
model-based way it doesn't seem like um
after a certain sort of level of
complexity to the the planning problem
that needs to be solved and then the the
other part is just tractability with you
know actually doing the modeling itself
because of just like how just um
intractably long it could take um to
actually run these simulations um and so
both both of those things kind of come
into play and it's not super clear
exactly how you know to address this I
mean there's there's certainly ideas out
there but most of them involve um taking
additional kind of machine learning
tricks um you know like adding like
adding like deep neural networks to
active inference models for example or
you know doing doing um you know very
various other sorts of um you know
little kind of heris short cuty things
that make stuff tractable right like not
actually searching all the way down
every possible branch of a decision tree
but using some heuristic to kind of say
two steps in or something no this Branch
seems bad I'm just G to cut this off and
not consider it anymore you know things
things like that or like sampling based
approaches um for exploring just kind of
little bits of a decision tree at a time
um you know it doesn't it's no longer
pure Act of inference anymore right I
mean it's it's a kind of combination of
active inference and a bunch of other
machine learning things um but you know
to a certain extent like that's probably
just like necessary and I mean bottom
line is the brain probably has to be
doing something other than fully model
based active inference um to be to be
tractable and so figuring out exactly
what parts of what the brain doing is
doing might be pure kind of active
influence and what parts are these other
things to to make stuff tractable um is
is I think part of the question yeah
look the scalability issue with active
inference it's not an active inference
issue it's just a basan learning and
decision-making issue yeah um it's
there's nothing inherent to active
inference that is that slows things down
um any any technique that can be used in
any any other sort of beian decision Mak
method can be used in active inference
um so yeah this is a the grand question
of how the brain is so efficiently able
to do this um where
there's yeah like Ryan said I mean you
run these very basic tasks and because
of this the exploding State space of uh
beijan decision- making right where just
these this exploding stat Bas of prob
probabilities um you get a massively
expanding search tree
ultimately and yeah nothing to do with
active inference of of course active
inference is um aan framework and so
it's it has to sort of use this um but
that's just a I mean if we can solve
this then uh that's
a yeah it would solve a lot of things if
it could solve how how we can perform
beian inference and especially B ban
inference in the service of decision-
making how we can do that very
efficiently um that would solve a lot of
things um um but as of yet yeah if we
want to try speed active inference up we
have to speed the general field of basan
decision making
up part I wasna
sorry okay I was just gonna say it's
part of it perhaps from a strategy
standpoint not trying to generate the
world's biggest plan but actually going
back to that rules business and saying
can we start there instead of a plan
that
because of its just its size makes
things intractable can we could we swap
something else in
for something we know won't work which
is world's biggest
plan um I mean I mean look there there's
lots of different you know things that
you know might you might consider like
like one one thing you know for these
like exploding decision tree um sorts of
problems is you know finding some way to
um chunk things together right to make
like the you know so for instance
instead of you know say I'm going to go
I decide I'm going to go walk to the
store or something right like in a
certain sense I've got a ton of
different options about you know where
to put my feet at each step and you know
like what door to go out of and things
like that um but it's not really clear
that when I'm planning like to go to the
store that I'm really explicitly
considering all of those details right
like I chunk it into you know I'm gonna
walk out to the street you know I'm
gonna walk you know 10 you know I'm GNA
walk a mile to the store and then I'm
going to walk into the store right in
which case if I've chunked that to just
kind of three steps right then my
decision tree is is already much more
tractable and then you just need to tell
some story about you know how you know
when we get to certain points in that
really abstract chunked um plan when we
get into those kind of Chunk States how
we make these kind of more local
decisions about what to do when at at
smaller scales like when we're in those
States so you know there's lots of kind
of hierarchical chunking is sorts of
things that you know you might think
that um the brain could be doing to make
these things tractable but and there's
lots of different kind of options on the
table and things that people um might
try but all things have certainly all
these things have not been um kind of
you know tested against Behavior yet to
see you know which ones are are are the
most plausible but there certainly
certainly different possibilities for
what might be going on
um you know another example you this is
something that we test empirically in my
lab right now is um the way people might
do something called like a verse of
pruning um and so so what you're kind of
doing there is you're just and this is
kind of similar to what I said before is
you know when you start kind of planning
down some tree if there's some early
outcome where you're imagining that it's
going to lead to some really negative
outcome right like on like if like on
step one or step two in a possible plan
I think oh there's going to be some big
negative thing then I will just no
longer simulate down the rest of that
Branch so it's a way of kind of reducing
the number of branches in a tray after
to search and um and so that's it's
often called again aversive aversive
decision tree pruning and that um you
know obviously you need to do something
like that right to keep it tractable but
at the same time it can cause problems
right because sometimes the best plan
might go through something negative in
the short term but lead to the best
thing in the long term right I mean so
that's the kind of thing we we test in
the lab is whether or not different
psychiatric conditions involve kind of
doing pruning too much right or too
little um and how that could lead to
suboptimal behavior in the long term um
the other I think the other aspect of
the the previous question you asked also
had to do with you know you read part of
the thing talking about um the uh the
the neural basis of of active inference
and how that should kind of remain
tentative and um just to kind of clarify
that a little bit I mean the the main
the main point is is just that again
this kind of involves being clear about
the separation between algorithm and
implementation right so the the
algorithm is basically just a
mathematics right that we um you know
that we kind of lay out but then the
implementation question is you know what
are the different possible ways you
could kind of set up the brain to to
carry out those equations and it's a
separate question what the you know how
the brain um how the brain was doing
that even if you think that there's good
reason to believe that the brain is
doing the doing something that's well
characterized by that the
mathematics um and um unlike predictive
coding which has been around a long time
and you know there's been much more
opportunity to test um at least um
qualitative predictions right you know
things like whether or not there's
evidence for like Omission responses in
the brain right like when there's the
lack of a stimulus when it was expected
leads to a neural response um which is
you know one of the stronger pieces of
evidence that the brain is doing
something predictive like predictive
coding um you know for for active
inference uh there really has been like
one Imaging study and it was done like
in 2015 and it was like an older version
of active inference it wasn't the
current for based on the current
formalism um you know so there's this
just just hasn't been done right and the
and even the um you know the little kind
of column structure things like what's
in the um like what's in the review in
our in our in this paper um is super
just kind of like promisory heuristic
sort of thing it's like here's a bunch
of here's a bunch of little balls that
will pretend are like neurons and here's
how you could connect them together
roughly you know to um do some sort of
you know some message passing algorithm
that you know you're thinking is you
know you're imagining or hypothesizing
is the is the one that the brain's doing
for this kind of approximate inference
process um and um you know even when it
comes
to um the current mathematical proposal
um for how the brain might be doing
something like this um there's different
hypotheses right so like initially most
people when they were doing simulations
with active inference models were
assuming um something called variational
message passing which is just a
particular way of kind of repeatedly
doing local approximate basian inference
on different kind of nodes in a graph um
and they youu this kind of over and over
again and thing kind of converges to a
good guess about what the posterior
should be over stes each time point
right but but you know then after that a
little bit more recently you know Thomas
par and Carl um and uh maybe other
people were on the paper I can't
remember they proposed a kind of updated
version of that called marginal message
passing um which is a little better um
it does a little it's slightly more it
can get it better um approximate
posteriors um you know on average um but
then there are others right there's
belief propagation as another sort of
message passing algorithm that's you
know been considered so there's a bunch
of these right and each of those even if
they're doing active inference right
like they will also predict different
neural Dynamics um so so those are also
even just active inference under what
message passing algorithm um separates
into a bunch of different competing
hypotheses about what you would measure
in the
brain awesome I'll read a question from
the live chat Andrew P
writes curious for Dr Smith where might
he place his previous work like
simulating the computational mechanisms
of cognitive and behavioral
psychotherapeutic interventions insights
from active inference in relation here
would this kind of work be more on the
side of theoretical
exploration like the cognitive affective
behavioral interactions construct or is
there a direction for empirical
testing I mean as is absolutely it was a
theoretical simulation work sort of
paper right I mean we weren't fitting
that model to any sort of empirical data
um it does I mean that one that paper in
particular does lend itself to at least
certain that that model is a little too
General like the patterns of behavior
that it predicts are really not specific
enough to like test in a you know some
sort of task um you could you could make
it you could modify it in a way that
might make it specific to some sort of
uh task that would involve um you know
specific sorts of explore exploit
decision-making choices under kind of
expected negative outcomes things like
that um but uh it does make a kind of
sort of qualitative prediction um that
could be that could be tested um you
know so one one one parameter that you
might fit right based on that model that
I think would be super interesting if
you could kind of turn it into a task is
this um parameter that reflects like the
degree to which your cognitive beliefs
influence your automatic effective
responses or expected effective
responses um the um so I mean it would
be really interesting to to try to use
that to figure out whether or not there
are we can measure individual
differences in this kind of what what
often gets called like cognitive
penetrability right so whether or not I
you know because I might explicit
believe I'm safe right in a certain
situation but I might see something that
still makes me feel really this
automatic kind of fear response in my
body or something even though I
explicitly believe it's safe right my
affective responses don't always have to
match my explicit cognitive thoughts
that's often a thing you see right in
people with with um with affective
disorders so this kind of individual
difference that you could estimate about
the degree to which these two um
essentially these two uh um
um different uh hidden State factors you
know in in the model the degree to which
those things interact effectively um but
the the other the other um prediction
that it makes um again it's a little
more qualitative but certainly something
that could be tested or made more
precise is um that you know in that in
that model um one of the the interesting
things that came out of the simulations
is that um you actually it's probably
actually not a good idea to make people
think that they're explicitly believe
that they're in a safe context um before
you do something like exposure therapy
um because if you do that then basically
what you're learning what the the
beliefs that you're updating in your
your likelihood right about like what
actions are going to lead to what
outcomes those will be updated under the
belief of safe context right so that
means all you have to do is switch back
to believing you're in the dangerous
context and then you're just right back
to the problematic avoidance behavior
again right um and this a bunch of other
there's recent empirical work that's um
very consistent with this idea actually
about you know explaining using this
kind of lateen causal inference um
framework not not an active inference in
particular but just Laden causal
inference more generally that um you
know to really get exposure therapy to
work long term um you need to kind of
prevent that people are inferring that
there's a new latent cause in operation
when people are doing exposure um
because otherwise they're they're just
learning safety under under a context
where they can really easily get the get
their um maladaptive avoidance to come
back just
spontaneously um just by kind of being
uncertain about the context they're in
later right like they're not they're not
actually unlearning the problematic
belief they're just inferring there's a
new cause where under that new cause
it's safe um so so it was much better um
the the prediction of that of that paper
would would be that could be tested
right and again like guess said there is
now some evidence consistent with this
um is that it's kind of better to do
things to keep people uncertain or keep
people believing that they're they're
still in the same context so that when
they go through this exposure therapy
and get unexpected outcomes they're
actually kind of overwriting their
previous beliefs as opposed to just
inferring they're in a new
Conta
awesome all right oh oh ask kind of
general question that that I'd love to
hear everyone's perspective
on we have active inference or
predictive coding or some other type of
formal framework that does interface
with empirical data like we're
discussing so on one hand we have the
empirical system or the measurements
coming from it existing data sets data
sets we create and so on and then on the
other side of this kind of statistical
interface is like numbers free energy
principle category Theory stuff that is
really
not having its validity or truth um or
Essence described by any particular
system so how do you just approach this
usefully as a graduate student
researcher or as like a broader clinical
research program and like think about
what system are you choosing what
statistical interface and how how
detailed do you go there and how do you
think about like what's on the other
side of the statistical interface
because a lot of times the discussion
around like the validity of active
inference and free energy principle is a
super philosophical question as if a
philosophical discussion would resolve
uncertainty about the empirical status
of active inference which is actually
the direction that you all took it from
the interface back to the system
rather than interface as outcome from
something theoretical to
debate um I feel like I have been kind
of hogging the show here a little so
I'll let um other people uh answer that
first at least um okay sorry those was
quite a long questions so I'm sorry if I
missed some of it um and just correct me
if I'm not answering right
uh I think I will talk on um this idea
between yeah on the one side uh sort of
mathematical formulations
representing something like uh brain
processes and then yeah sort of
mathematical formulations brain process
and behavior and um how these are sort
of seems as unified I think um as Ryan
said about uh talking about neuronal
implementation um there's many ways in
which um we could set up neuro like a
neur neural implementation to to uh
achieve um something like predictive
coding or active reference uh the same
goes
for algorithm where um there's many
different sort of forms of algorithms
could
achieve uh or statistical Windows as you
said if you want to go more broad um
could achieve the
same um neuronal implementation so uh
and then ultimately Behavior so uh in
terms of and please stop me if I'm not
answering correctly um but yeah in terms
of sort of as a graduate student
choosing what to focus on um I think
it's sort of a evolving process where
you constantly just try read and come up
with new ideas about how one can think
about how these can connect and how one
can represent the other um and and for
me it's been particularly interesting
just actually understanding what active
inference is in its um mathematical
Essence right we've got this first
principal account of it
um developed from the concepts of
homeostasis and yeah it's it's can
sometimes feel a bit strange when you
look at um quite simple mathematical
implementations in an algorithm and see
that well this isn't so different from
something like basan reinforcement
learning with specific directed
exploration um so there are these
there's a sense of of that sort of first
principal account um that comes all the
way from Mark of blankets um where is
that cap
in these algorithms and um that's
something I'm still trying to figure out
to be honest um it's I think it's it's
in in general it's a problem right to
and I think that's
why um when Ryan mentioned sort of uh
looking at more complex tasks I think
more complex tasks would allow us to
explore more complex representations of
of Act of inference um that can that can
perhaps capture um some of the
foundations that friston laid out
um so does that answer the question sort
of yeah that's awesome yeah I mean the
other I mean the other things I would
say I mean I think I understood at least
part of the question a little bit
differently um was that um you know
there's sort of what by that I don't
mean that you misunderstood Ro and you
just answered your different that's all
good my
answer uh part part of what I took your
question to be was something about you
know to what degree answers about the
you know quote unquote validity of
active inference or the free energy
principle can be established through
kind of like philosophical argument
versus what can be um or what needs to
be answered um through kind of direct
empirical
testing um and um and I think um you
know here I think it depends a little
bit right so I mean I think what you
know what philosophy is really good at
is actually more finding ways that
something couldn't be true
right I mean I take you know I mean I
have a philosophy background um as well
and I think I think philosophy is really
good at like conceptual analysis right
so trying to find you know where some
particular conceptual framework um you
know where there's tensions right or
where there's things that don't sort of
at first at first need sort of appear
and seem like they're contradictory have
some sort of internal tension um but
when you really drill down you find
certain contradictions right that you
know rule out something or make it
really
implausible um either through sort of
direct logical um um argumentation or um
through kind of like um just proposing
sort of thought experiments that that
really kind of pump intuitions in a way
that that make a difference so so I
think you can rule out with philosophy
philosophical methods um things that are
conceptually problematic right so you
can get down to kind of the set of
Frameworks or the set of yeah the set of
sort of interl Concepts that make of a
theory you can find a set of them that
are at least internally consistent and
and have some sort of General sort of
sufficient coherence to them but once
you've weeded things down to the kind of
subset of possible theories that are
internally consistent right and and
don't have any philosophical problems
associated with them then then I think
um things really kind of need to get
empirical um you know because because
you know to the extent that different
kind of competing um conceptual sort of
theoretical Frameworks to the extent
that they make different predictions um
and to the extent that the goal of this
whole project is to try to come up with
an accurate theory of what you know what
brains are doing right um if that is the
goal then the way the only way
ultimately to validate that is by
actually looking at brains and seeing
what they're actually doing um and um
and so and so I think I think that's
kind of where rubber meets the road WR a
bit right is this is that um um yeah you
need to know what's plausible right and
that's where I think philosophy can help
a lot but after you know what's
plausible then testing what's kind of
actual right is is is kind of the next
necessary step and um and this kind of
comes back to what Rowan was saying um
was that testing the unique predictions
of say some given active inference model
versus some competing model from another
framework like reinforcement learning um
can be tricky um usually you have to do
this in an incremental way and you do
that by finding by identifying some
prediction that is different between
those two models and then designing a
task that would really put people in a
decision in a in a position where they
have to make choices that are consistent
with either the prediction of one or the
other
um and um it really requires some
creativity right in coming up with the
right kind of to task with the right
sort of decision-making demands um and
constraints that will do that because
there's lots of tasks um where say the
kind of simplest most straightforward um
active inference model will really make
like almost exactly the same predictions
as what like a simpler reinforcement
learning model would make right so in
those cases you really can't
differentiate with two because they
pretty much predict the same thing
um and um you know as as Rowan mentioned
even though it's true that AC of
inference is kind of motivated from
these sort of first principles um which
is super nice um the the thing that you
ultimately end up converging on in terms
of the decision-making algorithms in
active inference start to look pretty
similar to the sorts of things that
people in machine learning and
reinforcement learning have ended up
kind of coming to anyway they just
haven't come to it from a first
principal perspective they've come to it
because they just kind of like tinkering
around and figure out what works um and
so um and so that that's also kind of an
interesting question is is you know
where can we find differences between
active inference and the other stuff
that's out there that has nothing that
has no connection to active inference
but it's kind of converged on a similar
type of solution um and um you know then
you get to a point where okay well if
we've gotten to the case where we have
two algorithms that have different
Origins but are basically doing the same
thing right then there is no competition
anymore we've just gotten to the same
solution two different ways um so that's
uh I don't know I guess I guess goes a
little bit beyond your question but but
I think um hopefully is all sufficiently
relevant that's awesome maybe um Marka
and then like kind of just in closing
here um how did people pick up and run
with the work and just how do people
continue with it but first how do you
approach this at a bigger level yeah um
so I come from like a different side to
this I come from more empirical
background like what Ryan was saying so
to me it's more about taking all of this
information kind of
accepting the broad literature that
that's out there not just in active
entrance or predictive coding but also
more from the psychology neoscience side
of things and kind of seeing where these
things fit in an empirical setting where
do these algorithmic ways um can be
tested in a plausible manner for example
like how Ryan was talking about uh the
last fmri study was done in like 201 uh
15 that actually tested like um active
inference models that to me is like the
first things where we would want to test
what is actually happening in the brain
whether it's through fmri EEG kind of
testing at different levels through
different computation models what the
brain is doing to me that's the most
interesting next step like taking the
computational work out there and trying
to relate it back to brain and
behavior
oh Rowan and then Ryan or anyone else
can just kind of give any last thoughts
or what they're going to take going
forward
go for it go for it ran if there's
anything you want to
say sorry I was muted um yeah I think I
think active inference is in a it's in
an interesting spot and um I think the
world of AI is in a very interesting
spot I know you know this uh by a I mean
artificial intelligence not active
inference um if we want to look at
active inflence as sort of um an element
of artificial intelligence um it repres
presents uh a side of things which is uh
sort of Neuroscience inspired artificial
intelligence um and as we all know
there's a there's a bit of a war going
on between that and um the large
language model and the kind of things um
and I think active inference is yeah I
think while it's tempting to sort of go
ahead with uh amassing more data and
training larger models um I think that
it's really important not to to forget
about this aspect of um trying to not
just come up with with you know more
architecture and more data but to come
up with more interesting Frameworks I
also think that unlike traditional
artificial intelligence or machine
learning um it's important to remember
that there's this tension between as we
mentioned before scalability and um and
just the efficiency and biological
plausibility we don't always want um a
solution a model to just be better and
quicker um that isn't necessary going
for we know that in many cases
artificial intelligence can do things
better and quicker than the human brain
but we shouldn't actually only care
about that sometimes um yeah it's
important to get a solution where it it
doesn't act more effectively but acts
more like um data empirical data that we
have gotten from actual human behavior
and that it even if it isn't the most
efficient sort of architectural
algorithmic structure it matches the
structure the brain might Implement so I
think it's important to remember these
factors um in this world where yeah it's
F developing into uh you know big data
and massive models um sometimes I find
myself uh drawn to just always trying to
make active reference faster and always
trying to make it more efficient and I
have to check myself with that um and
and remember what I'm actually
interested in so
yeah yeah and I guess I guess as a you
know concluding in my end I mean you
know Daniel you asked specifically kind
of about future directions um you know
and and the kind of thing that we're
doing in the lab right now is you know
very kind of inspired by what we said
you know needs to be done in the um in
the in the paper right I mean it's
always a little bit of an advertisement
for in a certain sense for you know
here's what we've done and here's what
needs to be done and you know then we're
trying to kind of Follow That ourselves
um but um you know and again you know
very much kind of in the context of of
trying to also use these Frameworks to
you know be of some kind of practical
benefit to the world right so I mean you
know we kind of in tandem right use this
as an opportunity to to one you know
test theories about you know how brains
and minds work but also to um take it as
a as a simultaneous opportunity to look
for where these sorts of mechanisms may
be um you know going wrong a bit and
people with different sorts of disorders
and whether or not that can um you know
give clinicians right like ideas for
novel treatment Target right like to
Target mechanism X versus y um you know
as kind of shown by what the differences
are in models when we fit them to
behavior and say like healthy versus
clinical
populations um and um and so you know
the sorts of things that you know we're
doing now on the on the cor of more
basic science side is is um you know I
have another grad student um coping um
Chia who's not on the call here but you
know she's done um some very extensive
work now fitting um um something like 50
or so different models um to um some
decision-making behavior that we have in
both a Taiwanese sample um where she's
from and and an American sample from
around here um and you know trying to
find right like which model fits best
and so these are a range of simpler kind
of reinforcement learning models and a
range of different active inference
models that is parameterized in
different ways right so ones that assume
sort of like you know static versus
Dynamic decision noise or static versus
Dynamic learning or I mean again there's
tons of little variants on these things
and so you know she's she's found in in
both samples that you know the model
that best fits the data um and wins in
model comparison is a is a specific um
active inference model that has six
parameters I think um that involves uh
you know dynamic learning or damic
decision noise that includes particular
sort of forgetting rate function um
that's you know not including Ed in kind
of the simplest version of active
inference um and um you know so showing
much more kind of conclusively in two
different data sets um you know that um
active inference um at least wins in
model comparison against some of these
other um uh other kind of competing
models um that being said I think it's
important that even though it wins in
model comparison when you actually look
at the predictive accuracies um they're
very similar you know we're talking
about active inference being able to
explain like 81 0 five% of the you know
like data versus uh the best
reinforcement lot reinforcement learning
model being able to pick like 80.6% of
the behavior you know so I mean these
differences are minor it comes down to
being better at predicting just a couple
of choices um but sometimes if those
choices follow from different sorts of
expected Dynamics along the way then
that can still be meaningful um you know
so that's the kind of thing you know
that we've been doing on the on the more
kind of basic science end that that
follows up on you know what we were
saying needs to be done um you know on
the sort of clinical end still not super
clinical is you know we have an A study
that we're that's ongoing right now um
that has both an online and a um
inperson component where we came up with
five different um five different tasks
that um where different models would
predict different patterns of behavior
um in distinct ways in each of those
tasks um a couple of them were designed
specifically for active inference um
others were designed like more in
relation to the hgf the hyan filter um
and um you know so we're in the process
of collecting a lot of data in those
where again we'll be able to fit
different models and um that one we're
also focusing a lot on um indiv on
whether or not we can find models and
parameter uh values in those models that
predict um individual differences and
subjective well-being um as well as um
negative effective stuff so we're trying
to go for not just pred like symptoms
and negative emotional stuff but also um
positive emotional stuff and what makes
a difference to decision patterns that
are say more consistent with um greater
satisfaction with life and subjective
wellbeing and things like that so um you
know we're doing that we're also doing
some computational sort of basian um
modeling of interception data so how
well people can like detect differences
in their um heartbeats or differences in
their kind of like respiratory
difficulty things like that um and how
they relates to anxiety disorders so so
we're um it's very much kind of a
combination of this basic science stuff
and the and trying to move the the
usefulness of this thing clinically at
the same time so it can be kind of
practically helpful to
people that's awesome Dean and then
anyone else and then that will be
awesome but where where where do you go
from here
Dean um have a shower I don't know I'm
not I don't have anything really planned
but I appreciate the uh I appreciate the
explanations and like I said when you
start from a place where you take two
things and hold them up together at the
same time that's that's the part that I
uh appreciate here and I think it again
reading through all of this um I didn't
understand all of the math but um it
also I think based B on what you were
able to show I wasn't sort of
questioning what what process you went
through to draw your conclusions and and
state what some of the limitations are
until those tests have have been uh
carried out so
yeah yeah thank you for the very clear
very relevant paper so good luck and
you're always welcome back to share more
we can follow up and um it'll be an
ongoing rolling literature meta analysis
across different systems there will be
thousands of fractal sub reviews
empirical status in the amydala on this
kind of thing so it's great to hear how
you did it this
time right thanks for having us yeah
thanks so much bye byebye
bye